Curriculum Vitae

Fabrizio Montesi

Personal and contact information

Name: Fabrizio Montesi

Citizenship: Italian

Languages: Italian (native), English (fluent), Danish (intermediate)

E-Mail: famontesi@gmail.com Web: http://www.fabriziomontesi.com/

Summary

I am an Assistant Professor in Computer Science working at the University of Southern Denmark, and a founder member of the Board of Directors at italianaSoftware s.r.l., Italy. I have 8 years of experience in the design and implementation of programming languages, software integration, and verification tools based on concurrency theory. I also have experience in teaching courses for university students and highly-trained professionals.

My scientific activities cover programming languages, distributed computing, software development, concurrency theory, formal logics, fault tolerance, and static analysis (e.g., type systems). For my work, I have received 1 research grant, 2 academic awards (for a paper and my M.Sc. thesis), 1 academic travel grant, and 3 business grants. My specialty is bringing together the theory and practice of concurrent systems. I maintain collaborations with several leading IT companies and agencies, e.g., Cognizant, ENEA (the Italian National Agency for New Technologies, Energy and Sustainable Economic Development), and SAP. I have a solid track record in the development of theoretical foundations and their technology transfer to real-world applications. My major achievements in the area are the co-creation of the Jolie programming language (for distributed systems that can natively integrate heterogeneous components), and several advancements in the field of bug-free distributed programming (with emphasis on choreographies and types).

Education

- 09/2010-08/2013: **Ph.D. Degree** at the IT University of Copenhagen, Denmark. Thesis title: "Choreographic Programming". Supervisor: Prof. Marco Carbone.
- 08/2011: attended NATO Summer School Marktoberdorf, Germany.
- 10/2006-07/2010: **M.Sc. Degree** in Computer Science, University of Bologna, Italy (obtained in date: 15/07/2010). Final mark: 110/110 cum laude. Thesis title: "Jolie: a service-oriented programming language". Supervisor: Prof. Gianluigi Zavattaro.
- 09/2003-12/2006: **B.Sc. Degree** in Computer Science, University of Bologna, Italy (obtained in date: 21/12/2006). Final mark: 110/110 cum laude. Thesis title: "Design and development of JOLIE, a language for service orchestration". Supervisor: Prof. Gianluigi Zavattaro.

Current and Previous Positions

- 08/2014-current: **Assistant Professor** at the University of Southern Denmark.
- 09/2013-07/2013: **Postdoctoral Researcher** at the IT University of Copenhagen, Denmark.
- 09/2010-08/2013: **Ph.D. student fellow** at the IT University of Copenhagen, Denmark.
- 04/2008-current: Founder Member of the board of directors at italianaSoftware s.r.l., Italy.
- 03/2007-02/2009: **Independent research fellow** at the University of Bologna, Italy, Department of Computer Science, for the EU Integrated Project SENSORIA.
- 06/2007-06/2009: **Freelance** (self-employed) software analyst and developer.

Grants and Awards

- 2014: **Principal Investigator** of *Choreographies for Reliable and efficient Communication software* (*CRC*), a 2.4 million DKK **research grant** from The Danish Council for Independent Research Technology and Production Sciences (DFF-FTP).
- 2013: SIGPLAN Professional Activities Committee (PAC) travel grant for ACM POPL 2013.
- 2013: Best Poster Award at the ACM SAC 2013 conference.
- 2011: Confindustria/CINI Italian national award for best M.Sc. thesis on ICT of "Particular relevance in Computer Science".
- 2008: I TECH-OFF **business grant**, with italianaSoftware s.r.l. The Italian business grant for the support of new and innovative ICT companies.
- 2007: Ingenium **business grant**, jointly with Claudio Guidi. A grant for the creation and support of business ideas with strong growth potential.
- 2007: Start Cup **business grant**, jointly with Claudio Guidi, for the creation of italianaSoftware s.r.l. The Italian grant for excellent business plans on technology and innovation.

Management Experience

- 10/2013-current: **vice-chair** of the working group on Tools and Applications in Behavioural Types for Reliable Large Software Systems (BETTY), European COST Action IC1201.
- 03/2006-current: administrator of the Jolie open source project.
- 04/2008-08/2010: **project manager** at italianaSoftware s.r.l., Italy, for research and development of language-based programming tools for the development of distributed systems.

International Relations

- 01/2013-current: **member** of the Jolie research laboratory at the University of Bologna, Italy.
- 08/2012-09/2012: visiting researcher at Imperial College London, UK.
- 11/2009-current: **external collaborator** of the FOCUS Research Team, INRIA, France / University of Bologna, Italy.
- 03/2007-02/2010: **member** of Software Engineering for Service-Oriented Overlay Computers (SEN-SORIA), European Integrated Project in the 6th Framework Programme (FP6).

Journal and Conference organisation, PC memberships, Refereeing

- Co-Editor "Special Issue: Service-Oriented Architectures and Programming 2014", to appear in Journal of Internet Services and Information Security (JISIS).
- PC member "SI on Knowledge Intensive Systems and Services", to appear in *International Journal of Systems and Service-Oriented Engineering (IJSSOE)*.
- Co-Editor "Special Issue: Service-Oriented Architectures and Programming 2013", Science of Computer Programming (SCP), Vol. 97, 2015.
- Steering Committee member 29th ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC), Service-Oriented Applications and Programming track (SOAP), 2015.
- PC member 29th ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC), Service-Oriented Applications and Programming track (SOAP), 2015.
- **PC member** 29th ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC), Operating Systems track (OS), 2015.
- **PC member** Programming Language Approaches to Communication- and concurrency-cEntric Systems (PLACES), 2015.
- **PC member** 11th Workshop on Automated Specification and Verification of Web Systems (WWV), 2015.
- **PC member** 6th International Conference on Ambient Systems, Networks and Technologies (ANT), 2015.

- PC member World Conference on Information Systems and Technologies (WorldCIST), 2015.
- Track program chair 28th ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC), Service-Oriented Applications and Programming track (SOAP), 2014.
- PC member World Conference on Information Systems and Technologies (WorldCIST), 2014.
- **PC member** 6th International Conference on Advanced Service Computing (Service Computation), 2014.
- Track program chair 27th ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC), Service-Oriented Applications and Programming track (SOAP), 2013.
- PC member World Conference on Information Systems and Technologies (WorldCIST), 2013.
- Track program chair 26th ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC), Service-Oriented Applications and Programming track (SOAP), 2012.
- PC member 25th ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC), 2011.
- PC member 24th ACM Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC), 2010.
- Referee for several international journals, conferences and workshops including IJCM, IJSSOE, JCCBS, MSCS, SCP, CONCUR, ESOP, FMOODS, FSEN, LICS, SAC, TGC, WorldCIST, WS-FM.

Invited Seminars and Lectures

- 2014: Choreographic Programming. Invited keynote talk, 11th International Workshop on Web Services and Formal Methods: Formal Aspects of Service-Oriented and Cloud Computing (WS-FM: FASOCC).
- 2014: Software Integration and Services. Invited talk at Spitze & Co, Denmark.
- 2013: Service-oriented Computing and the Jolie language. Invited M.Sc. lecture at the Technical University of Denmark (DTU), "Distributed Systems" course, Copenhagen, Denmark.
- 2013: Deadlock-freedom-by-design: Global Programming with Chor. Invited seminar at the New University of Lisbon, Portugal.
- 2012: Deadlock-freedom-by-design: Multiparty Asynchronous Global Programming. Invited seminar at University College London, UK.
- 2012: Deadlock-freedom-by-design: Global Programming with Chor. Invited seminar at Cognizant, UK.
- 2012: The Chor language. Invited seminar at Queen Mary University of London, UK.
- 2012: Global Programming with Chor. Invited seminar at Imperial College London, UK.
- 2012: Service-oriented Computing and the Jolie language. Invited M.Sc. lecture at the Technical University of Denmark (DTU), "Distributed Systems" course, Copenhagen, Denmark.
- 2011: Jolie: a Service-oriented Programming Language. Invited talk at the Programming Languages Day at INRIA, Sophia Antipolis, France.
- 2009: Jolie: a language for Service-oriented Computing. Invited seminar at INRIA, Sophia Antipolis, France.

Conference and Workshop Presentations

- 2014: Choreographies, Logically. 25th International Conference on Concurrency Theory (CONCUR), Rome (Italy).
- 2013: Compositional Choreographies. 24th International Conference on Concurrency Theory (CONCUR), Buenos Aires (Argentina).
- 2013: Deadlock-freedom-by-design: Multiparty Asynchronous Global Programming. 40th ACM SIGPLAN-SIGACT Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages (POPL), Rome (Italy).
- 2012: Merging Multiparty Protocols in Multiparty Choreographies. Programming Language Approaches to Concurrency and Communication-cEntric Software (PLACES) workshop, Tallinn (Estonia).

- 2011: Programming services with correlation sets. 10th International Conference on Service-Oriented Computing (ICSOC), Paphos (Cyprus).
- 2010: A model of evolvable components. 5th Symposium on Trustworthy Global Computing (TGC), Munich (Germany).
- 2008: Connecting Plasma to service-oriented programming with Jolie. KDE's Free Software Desktop Summit (Akademy), Sint-Katelijne-Waver (Belgium).
- 2007: Composing services with Jolie. 5th IEEE European Conference on Web Services (ECOWS), Halle (Germany).
- 2006: Jolie: a Java Orchestration Language Interpreter Engine. 2nd International Workshop on Coordination and Organization (CoOrg), Bologna (Italy).